<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Candor Citadel</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-03-29T13:03:58+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Candor Citadel</name>
   <email>candorcitadel@protonmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The Innocent Culprit</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/the-innocent-culprit/"/>
   <updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/the-innocent-culprit</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;– &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are an arsonist. You douse the grass in gasoline. You ignite it with a burning matchstick. You let it develop into a forest fire. What caused the fire, and how do we know?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– &lt;em&gt;I caused the fire, of course. There would be no fire without me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;There would be no fire without grass, trees, or oxygen either. Did they cause the fire too?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing the &lt;cite&gt;“innocent culprit”&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be argued that trees are the cause of forest fires, and convincingly so. Research will show that forest fires have a 100% association with the presence of trees, while only a fraction of forest fires are associated with the presence of arsonists. Further highly technical thermodynamic analyses would determine the presence of trees as an absolute requirement for the development forest fires. Finally, experimental tree-cutting would show correlations between the number of trees and both the frequency and severity of forest fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, this is absurd. We know it is absurd because we know what trees, forests, and arsonists are, and have a good understanding of the whole picture. Trees, grass, oxygen, arsonists are all “causes” of forest fires. Attempting to understand a multifactorial phenomenon by analyzing one factor in isolation can lead to disastrous conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we are able to recognize the insanity of the depicted research on forest fires and avoid a disaster by realizing that trees are &lt;em&gt;innocent culprits&lt;/em&gt;. But what if we weren’t? What if the research was on something we were unfamiliar with? Sadly, this nonsense is widespread in current research. While many are aware of the fact that correlation does not imply causation&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tylervigen.com/spurious-correlations&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Correlation_does_not_imply_causation&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, few realize that causation does not imply that you have found the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As illustrated here, finding causation is in many cases meaningless and should not be the end goal of scientific research. This post will serve as an reference for future citations of the term &lt;cite&gt;“innocent culprit”&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
